I took a bike trip to Xinjiang in 2019.
Though fun from riding was the main motive then,
this thousand-mile trip to Xinjiang was for something totally different.
There was a piece from Buzzfeed a while back,
supposedly locating many concentration camps in Xinjiang using satellite imagery.
But due to Chinese government policies,
it's now very difficult for foreign journalists to report in Xinjiang.
I thought,
"Foreign journalists can't enter,
but I can."
Besides, the aim of this series of films was
to record meaningful things.
I won't just eat, drink and be merry.
There is only satellite imagery on the website.
Where the marked buildings specifically are,
How they really look,
And how their surroudings are -
I returned to Xinjiang with those doubts.
I encounter two checkpoints right off the expressway in the eastern outskirts of Kumul.
The first is expected,
but I don't foresee another police check at a village junction.
Tourists aren't usually here
so I initially don't turn in
visiting the corner shop instead
Here, I pretend to be a tourist buying things.
But the police officer doesn't stop me.
He's obviously not interested in my car with inter-provincial plates.
This side street runs parallel to the Lianhuo Expressway
with many fields and farmhouses alongside.
Because the Mapbox imagery was captured before 2017,
and ones found on Baidu are medium-res imagery from faraway,
I can only rely on some obvious, unchanging characteristics.
to locate them on normal road maps.
The first gray target to be filmed is here in North Village (北村).
There is a brand new yet narrow paved road
that is however not shown on Baidu maps.
The asphalt road seems quite suspicious,
as most roads of this width in Xinjiang are made of dirt.
Cotton occupies the surroudings.
A pink building lies in the distance.
seemingly out of place among the surrouding farmhouses.
But closed-off windows and wire fences aren't seen by this building,
and it's a gray target.
I don't observe closely,
only counting it as something suspicious.
I don't dare go too near
as I was quite anxious,
learning from the last drone incident in Tibet.
I don't want to run right into the police the first time filming,
so my movement is very cautious.
And another note:
I haven't recorded any on-scene commentary during the whole course
because of safety concerns.
Since if I recorded a piece of commentary,
"This is a concentration camp in ... in Xinjiang",
and were then stopped by police to check the footage,
then I myself would be in a concentration camp.
Going west towards Kumul City on country roads,
passing by Kumul Train Station,
I arrive at Advance (前進) Avenue and August First North (八一北) Road.
Here is a yellow target.
The garden to the east is easily distinguishable.
The target lies to the west.
Only after passing the intersection do I notice this being the Kumul Compulsory Drug Qurantine Treatment Centre,
neighboured by an apartment complex.
The Drug Treatment Centre is not marked on Baidu Maps.
All windows are closed off.
There is also barbed wire atop the walls.
The facilities here are totally capable of being used as a concentration camp.
But as the data from Mapbox is way too old,
being much different to the present situation.
So it can be considered likely, but not certain.
The "Drug Treatment Centre" lies on the yellow target.
There is a red target near Beijiao (北郊) Road in Kumul,
adjacent to 康和雅居社區.
Before driving into this small alleyway,
I first buy some stuff in the shop adjacent.
The gate shield says "Thirteenth Division Detention Centre" -
a government facility, it seems.
Cameras are everywhere.
I don't at all dare exiting the car to film.
I initially want to exit through the road's other end,
but find no way.
There is also barbed wire on the wall opposite the detention centre.
I can't risk staying longer,
pretending to have gone the wrong way, and leave.
This detention centre is also not marked on Baidu Maps.
On the second day, I head north from 天山,
first arriving in 木壘哈薩克自治縣.
On satellite imagery, I notice two targets slightly far from the road.
The other side are fields without much cover.
I think it's convenient to film,
but notice, as I near the centre of the fields,
it's prone to attracting people's attention -
not an optimal filming position.
I then try filming from another positiont
Guard towers and barbed wire are after all visible,
matching the yellow target's description.
But the precise locations of the two targets on the road map can't be confirmed.
At last, I head north from 人民南路.
Here lies 有農牧民 Training Centre.
with "Vocational Training Centre" written on the wall
and barbed wire atop the walls,
which match characteristics of the gray targets.
Further up the road, a shield to the side says "Vocational Training Centre".
This should be the location of the watchtowers shown just then.
And then passing a health centre,
which is marked on Baidu Maps.
But neither the training centre nor detention centre is.
According to the above observations,
these two targets should be 木壘縣 Detention Centre and 農牧民 Training Centre.
Going west towards 達吉木薩爾縣,
there is a yellow target,
quite recognisable on satellite maps,
lying on the north-west corner of Xiyu (西域) Road and West People's (人民西) Road.
It's nothingness on Baidu Maps,
but actually 吉木薩爾縣 Detention Centre.
Because of the tall walls,
only the walls and guardtowers can be filmed.
There are three targets in 阜康市 to the west.
Let's first visit this dark red target.
I carefully compare the blurry Baidu satellite imagery and Mapbox data,
confirming this location to be likely to
the northwest of G335國道寧朔路 and 南華路.
But it's not found nearby,
only an abandoned yard.
So either I'm wrong and can't find the place,
or the BFN website is wrong.
Going a bit further west along the G335 National Road,
there is a north-south unnamed road,
lying west of the Y109 Village Road.
Things like "軍墾農場" and "水磨新村" are marked on Baidu Maps.
The other two targets in Fukang are north of this unnamed road.
Barbed wires and watchtowers are clearly visible.
This should be the Fukang Detention Centre.
There are many targets in and around Urumqi.
I only visit four of them.
Three northern ones are north of 城北大道 and 東站路.
There is the marking "Urumqi市第二教育矯治局" on Baidu Maps.
This so-called 矯治局 actually also has a barb-wired courtyard.
There are surveilliance cameras once every few dozen metres.
To ensure filming quality,
I have to put on my backpack and strap on my camera.
This backpack mades me look unnatural.
Why would tourists come here?
I could only pray that no guards notice me.
After walking around, I notice:
There are not only three places walled off with barbed-wire.
I then drive once more around,
noticing a vegetable-tranport vehicle parked in front of a concentration camp.
Going further north,
passing an entrance of 第二矯治局
a strigently iron-fenced gate is seen.
So the 教育矯治局 is highly likely
to be also used as a low-security concentration camp.
Northwards, there is a road running east to west
which isn't marked on Baidu Maps.
The street sign says Gaoke (高科) Road.
There are multiple large concentration areas south of this street,
all with guarded watchtowers.
高科路 is approximately 1.1 kilometres, measured using Baidu Maps.
Judging by the scale, many people are probably imprisoned here.
This is probably the largest concentration camp in Urumqi.
Note here the slogan on the roof:
The four characters, "Labour transformation", "cultural transformation", are faintly visible.
This red target south of Urumqi is actually Xishan (西山) Detention Centre.
Its location is clearly seen from the hilltop in Ya'shan (雅山) Park.
The characters "Fifth Captivity Area" stands atop a glass gate.
Glass rooftops protrude the buildings.
Inmates can presumably only breathe fresh air indoors.
Leaving Urumqi for Dawan Cheng,
there is an unremarkable small street off the G312 National Road.
Passing a railway bridge,
the road quickly becomes gravel.
I once again end up somewhere, where tourists shouldn't be.
Opposite the hill is a newly built, uncommissioned concentration camp.
As no cover is nearby, I can only crawl up the hill and film,
not risking getting caught by standing.
There is also another target in Dawan Cheng.
Presumably a detention centre, but I don't visit.
I go to the eastern outskirts of Korla on the last day.
This here is nothingness on Baidu Maps,
but information from BFN shows multiple concentration camps.
Heading towards the G218 National Road from the Northern Ring Road,
a Party's Defence Army garrison first lies,
clearly visible on Mapbox satellite maps.
Two tanks also occupy the garrison,
resembling the model that ran people over at Tian'anmen.
It actually isn't.
There is more than one garrison around here.
The nearby buildings might be barracks,
or other facilities.
There are many military trucks parked in the yard,
with likely many Party's Defence Army troops stationed here.
Behind those barracks,
there are barb-wired walls with watchtowers farther in the distance.
There lies the concentration camp.
I initially want to go nearer,
but there is unfortunaly no way there.
The last stop, Karasahr City Centre, has two targets.
First arriving at the northern bank of the Kaidu River,
stopping by an unnamed road,
newly built walls and watchtowers are filmed.
There is also a ring of buildings near the concentration camp.
There is a yellow target here.
The concentration camp is hidden behind this big red gate,
not easily noticeable driving by on the road.
河對面橋頭的位置是另外一個灰色標記所在
在橋上就能看見高大的黃色建築
There are only walls without barbed-wire or watchtowers;
windows are also not barred -
like the pink houses first seen in Kumul.
Buildings marked gray don't seem to be concentration camps.
Those were my on-site observations.
Due to the limited time and far distance,
I only investigated a few selected targets.
Most importantly, I could only film very limited footage before the walls.
More data of the same category would be quite meaningless anyway.
There are already many reports over concentration camps in Xinjiang by foreign media.
The last time I motorcycled there, I asked the local Han people,
some revealing Uyghur people being dedicated elsewhere as cheap labour.
Those Uyghurs who don't want to snitch on their compatriots for the Chinese Government
are also lead into concentration camps for re-education.
The Uyghur language is not allowed in schools.
During the 2019 Hong Kong Anti-Extradition Movement,
Chinese Government-controlled police personell
dared to relentlessly beat and kill people in front of so many foreign journalists.
Therefore, in somewhere like Xinjiang, where foreign can't at all enter,
abuse of the Uyghur people by the Chinese Government is even more unimaginable.
One who doesn't wish to be enslaved also doesn't want others enslaved.
May the Chinese Government, the CCP, soon dissolve and step down,
end these crimes against humanity.